Guide to the Arthur Machen Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Arthur Machen collection
1888-1958
GEN MSS 256
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.2
(11 boxes)
Contains correspondence to, from, and about Machen. Correspondents include Aldrich Munson Havens, Charles Parsons, and Vincent Starrett, among others. Also contains holograph, typescript, and proof versions of Machen's writings, such as "The Garden of Avallaunius", "The Memoirs of Jacques Casanova", and "The Secret Glory."
Machen, Arthur, 1863-1947
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Restricted Fragile Papers in Box 11 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Arthur Machen, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Authors, English -- Archives; Garden of Avallaunius; Memoirs of Jacques Casanova; Secret glory; Havens, Munson Aldrich, 1873-1942; Machen, Arthur, 1863-1947; Parsons, Charles, 1889-; Starrett, Vincent, 1886-1974
- Materials Given by Charles Parsons, Series I
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Arthur Machen
      - 6 ALS to Munson Havens, London, 1923-25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 12 ALS to Charles Parsons, London, 1924-26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Scope and Contents
        Includes 12 envelopes; laid in are two telegrams with addressed envelope (London, 1925 Oct 5).
      - ALS to Charles Parsons, London, 1926 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Concerning Eleusinia; with receipt.
      - Addressed envelope (front only) to Charles Starrett, of Chicago Daily News, 1916 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Removed from: Angels of Mons by Arthur Machen (London, 1915).
      - 5 envelopes addressed in Machen's hand to Vincent Starrett, London, [1917?]-22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Probably enclosing the advance proof sheets of some of his writings, such as "The Hill of Dreams" and "The Shining Pyramid."
    - Letters to Arthur Machen
      - Wells, Thomas B. TLS, 1918 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Regarding the publication of his book of remembrances.
    - Third Party Correspondence
      - Armstrong, Terence Ian Fytton. Christmas card to Charles Parsons, 1930 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Displays portrait of Arthur Machen by Edward A. Gordon Craig; with autograph envelope.
      - Balch, Emily Tapscott (Clark). ALS to Charles Parsons, Richmond, Va., 1924 Jul 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Referring to Machen; with envelope.
      - Begbie, Harold. ALS to Vincent Starrett, Garden court, Swanage, 1922 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Referring to Machen.
      - [Best?]. ALS to Mr. Starrett, 1923 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Removed from: Angels of Mons by I. E. Taylor (London, 1916).
      - Danielson, Henry. TLS to Mr. Starrett, [London], 1923 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Referring to the Machen bibliography.
      - Darlington, H. S. 2 TLS to Charles Parsons, Ada, Oklahoma, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Enclosing his "Synopsis and Interpretation of The Hill of Dreams by Arthur Machen."
      - Deland, Margaret Wade (Campbell). TLS to Charles Parsons, Boston, 1923 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Dictated with manuscript note by the author, criticizing Machen's writings and mentioning Sinclair Lewis' Babbitt; with envelope.
      - Dulau and Company, Ltd. TL with illegible signature to Charles Parsons, London, 1926 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Mentioning a Machen article.
      - Eddy, Frederick B. TLS to Charles Parsons, New York, 1923 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        About Arthur Machen; enclosed is a carbon copy of Machen's article, "Edgar Allan Poe, the Supreme Realist"; with addressed envelope.
      - Grant, D. E. 4 TLS to Charles Parsons, New York, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Referring to Arthur Machen.
      - [Greb?] Bohun. ALS to Vincent Starrett, [London], 1922 Sep 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Referring to a caricature of Arthur Machen.
      - Green, Donald E. ALS to Vincent Starrett, Caerleon, England, 1922 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Referring to Machen's Eleusinia.
      - Havens, Munson. 7 TLS to Charles Parsons, Cleveland, 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Mentioning Mr. Machen and editions of his works; includes some envelopes.
      - Hill, Walter Martin. 4 TLS, 2 ALS and an envelope addressed to Charles Parsons, Chicago, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Concerning the purchase of the Starrett-Machen collection, including an inventory of the collection; laid in are two receipted bills in payment for Machen's Don Quixote, Way to Attain, and The Hill of Dreams.
      - Knollenberg, Bernhard. 2 TLS to Charles Parsons, New Haven, Conn., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Marks, Harry F. 2 TLS to Charles Parsons, [New York?], 1924 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Mentioning Machen's writings.
      - Mayfield, John S. TLS to D. E. Grant, Washington, D.C., 1927 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        In reference to a Machen item.
      - Millard, Christopher Sclater. 2 TLS to Vincent Starrett, London, 1920, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        About Machen's writings.
      - Phillips, A. TLS to Vincent Starrett, [London], 1923 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Regarding a pamphlet: "Parsifal," for his Machen collection.
      - Smith, Paul Jordan. 2 TLS to Charles Parsons, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        Concerning Arthur Machen.
      - Smith, Paul Jordan. ALS, TLS & APS to Vincent Starrett, 1920-22 (Box 1, Folder 27)
        Describing his visit to the Hardys, to Stoke Poges, and to Machen.
      - Spurr, Harry. TLS to Vincent Starrett, London, 1922 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Referring to Arthur Machen and others.
      - Starrett, Vincent. 3 TLS, 3 ALS, and an envelope addressed to Mr. Parsons, Chicago, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Including two check-lists of the collection, and a list of Starrett's writings.
      - Van Patten, Nathan. TLS to Charles Parsons, Stanford, Calif., 1949 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Waite, Arthur Edward. ALS and 2 signed postcards to Vincent Starrett, Ramsgate, England, 1921-22 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        About Machen items.
      - 5 TLS and 5 ALS from various publishers to various people, 1919-24, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Relating to the published works of Arthur Machen; with one clipping.
  - WRITINGS OF ARTHUR MACHEN
    - "Ballad of the Armed Man," [London?], [1888?] (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Original autograph manuscript with title, "An excellent ballad of the Armed Man, very pleasent & profitable for the present times by Arthur Machen, gent."; laid in is a manuscript note, signed, explaining the composing of the "Armed Man" (1924 Sep).
    - Biographical and critical manuscript notes (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Published as pages 14, 28, and 49-55 of Arthur Machen: A Bibliography by Henry Danielson (London, 1923).
    - "The Capital Levy, An Essay in Economics," [London?] (Box 1, Folder 35)
      An original manuscript in the author's autograph, signed.
    - "The Confessions of a Literary Man", 1922 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Newspaper clipping from the Evening News (London, 1915 Mar-Jun), signed and corrected in the author's hand as he prepared the text for publishing in book form by Martin Secker under the title, "Far Off Things."
    - "Conjuring Time," [London], 1922 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Galley proof, signed by the author and dated.
    - "The Garden of Avallaunius"
      - Original autograph manuscript, 1922 Sep 25 (Box 2, Folder 38)
        Signed at end; added manuscript title page; afterwards called "The Hill of Dreams."
      - Page proof, corrected in the author's hand, signed, and dated, 1904 Nov 2 (Box 3, Folder 39)
        Laid in: contract with Alfred Wareing for publishing the book described above, London, 1903 Aug 20.
    - "The Grande Trouvaille (A Legend of Pentonville)", 1923 Mar (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Page proofs for "A Catalogue of Rare Books," No. 2; with manuscript corrections.
    - "The Memoirs of Jacques Casanova" translated by Machen
      - Original autograph manuscript in pencil of the preface of his English translation, [1894?] (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club?], Volume I, [1940?] (Box 3, Folder 42-49)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club], Volume II, [1940?] (Box 4, Folder 50-55)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club], Volume III, [1940?] (Box 4, Folder 56-61)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club], Volume IV, [1940?] (Box 5, Folder 62-67)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club], Volume V, [1940?] (Box 5, Folder 68-72)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club], Volume VI, [1940?] (Box 6, Folder 73-77)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club], Volume VII, [1940?] (Box 6, Folder 78-84)
      - Translator's original material for [Limited Editions Club], Volume VIII, [1940?] (Box 7, Folder 85-91)
      - "Author's Preface," first proof sheets, [1940?] (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - "Translator's Preface," holograph, signed, [1940?] (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - "Translator's Preface," first proof sheets with manuscript corrections in ink, [1940?] (Box 8, Folder 94)
      - Galley proof of the Preface to the translation into English of the 1922 edition, [1922?] May 15 (Box 8, Folder 95)
        With autograph corrections and added notes, signed, and envelope, addressed to Frederick B. Eddy, Esq.
      - Galley proof of the Preface to the translation into English of the 1922 edition, [1922?] May 15 (Box 8, Folder 96)
        Unsigned; laid in: TLS to Mr. Starrett, signed John Rodker, enclosing the advance proof of Mr. Machen's Preface, London, 1922 May 15; laid in: envelope with a pencilled note, probably by V. Starrett, post-marked London, 1922 May 15, presumably from John Rodker, enclosing the galley proof of the "Preface."
    - The Physiology of Taste by Jean Anthelme Brillat-Savarin. Introduction, London, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 97)
      Autograph manuscript and 2 sets of proof sheets.
    - "The Secret Glory"
      - Autograph manuscript of Section V use restricted; see note laid in, [1922?] (Box 8, Folder 98-100)
      - Page proof, London, [1922?] (Box 8, Folder 101)
        Revised with pencilled corrections in the author's hand; laid in: envelope, addressed to Vincent Starrett of Chicago.
    - "A Secret Language," [London?] (Box 8, Folder 102)
      Original autograph manuscript signed.
    - "Inscription for the Tomb of Tom, a Black Cat, Who for More Than Sixteen Years was a Faithful Servant of the House of Machen", n.d. (Box 8, Folder 103)
      Autograph manuscript.
    - Autograph quotation, 1924 Feb 25 (Box 8, Folder 104)
      Inscribed "For Charles Parsons"; begins "Sorcery and sanctity, said Ambrose, 'thers are the only realities..."; accompanied by a photograph of Machen by E. O. Hoppe; mounted and framed.
  - OTHER
    - Danielson, Henry. A Bibliography of Arthur Machen, 1922 Sep 25 (Box 8, Folder 105)
      Two sets of corrected galley proofs, with typewritten additions; one set of page proofs; each set is signed and dated.
    - Sime, Sidney H. Frontispiece to Arthur Machen's Hill of Dreams, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 106)
      Original ink wash drawing; autograph of Arthur Machen on verso of drawing.
    - Starrett, Vincent
      - Arthur Machen, A Novelist of Ecstasy and Sin, [Chicago?], [1923?] (Box 8, Folder 107)
        Galley proofs with autograph corrections in ink.
      - Introduction to the Shining Pyramid, Chicago, [1923] (Box 8, Folder 108)
        Page proof, signed.
- Additional Materials, Series II
  Received from various sources.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Arthur Machen
      - ALS to James T. Babb, High St., Old Amersham, Bucks, 1940 Jun 21 (Box 9, Folder 109)
        With addressed envelope. Gift, 1940.
      - ALS to Mr. Cazenova, St. Marylebone, N.W., 1910 Jan 28 (Box 9, Folder 110)
        On literary business. Purchase, 1942.
      - 45 ALS to W. J. T. Collins, 1922-46 (Box 9, Folder 111)
        Accompanied by autograph manuscript of Machen's Romance and Reality. Purchase, 1954.
      - ALS to F. C. Davis, Buckinghamshire, 1945 Sep 8 (Box 9, Folder 112)
        Eulogizing W. J. T. Collins. Purchase, 1954.
      - ALS to Mr. Ellis, London, 1922 [Sep 29] (Box 9, Folder 113)
        Purchase, 1956.
      - Typed copies of 26 letters to Montgomery Evans, II, 1923-31 (Box 9, Folder 114)
        Laid in: Typed copy of Evans' letter to Machen, 1923 Sep 12. Gift, 1940.
      - 13 ALS and 3 APcS to Kyrle Fletcher and Ifan Kyrle Fletcher (Box 9, Folder 115)
        Reader notes by Arthur Machen on verso of a manuscript fragment, "A Message of Thanks"; prospectus for a birthday tribute for Arthur Machen. Purchase, 1997.
      - ALS to Borne Granger, 12 Melina Place, London, 1923 Mar 5 (Box 9, Folder 116)
      - ALS to Mr. Ransome, London, 1910 Dec 5 (Box 9, Folder 117)
        Discussing Edgar Allen Poe and the sources for the "Raven." Purchase, 1942.
      - 7 ALS to Arnold Rubin, 1928-32 (Box 9, Folder 118)
        Containing literary criticisms and suggestions for interesting reading; with three envelopes. Purchase, 1941.
      - ALS to Mr. Smith, London, 1923 Dec 4 (Box 9, Folder 119)
        Mentioning Henry Savage. Purchase, 1942.
      - 2 ALS to Harold Wilenski, 1929, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 120)
        Concerning Far Off Things by Machen, and concerning literature as a profession; with one envelope. Purchase, 1941.
      - ALS to Charles Wilson, London, 1927 Nov 24 (Box 9, Folder 121)
        With envelope. Gift, 1943.
      - 2 ALS to "Crippin," London, 1914, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 122)
        Possibly to Henry Durrell Crippin. Gift, 1964.
      - ALS to "Dear People of Gwent," Buckinghamshire, 1943 Mar 3 (Box 9, Folder 123)
        Purchase, 1954.
      - ALS to "My Dear Savage," [London], 1915 Mar 23 (Box 9, Folder 124)
        Possibly to Henry Savage; removed from: The Hill of Dreams by Arthur Machen (London, 1907). Gift, 1959.
    - Third Party Letters
      - Knopf, Alfred. TLS to Donald Wing, New York, 1943 Mar 29 (Box 9, Folder 125)
        Accompanied by clipping with reference to financial aid to be given to Machen. Gift, 1943.
  - WRITINGS OF ARTHUR MACHEN
    - "The Children of the Pool and other Stories," London, [1936] (Box 9, Folder 126)
      Galley proofs, with manuscript corrections throughout.
    - "The Collector's Craft," London
      - Original holograph manuscript, 1930 May 10 (Box 9, Folder 127)
        Inscribed to Fytton Armstrong and dated.
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 128)
        With manuscript corrections, signed; the title is "The Craft of the Collector."
      - Galley proofs, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 129)
        For "A Catalogue of Rare Books"; the title is "The Craft of the Collector."
      - Page proofs, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 130)
        For "A Catalogue of Rare Books"; with manuscript corrections.
      - Printed version, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 131)
        In the First Edition Bookshop's "A Catalogue of Rare Books," No. 6.
      - Privately printed edition, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 132)
        Inside: "This edition consists of two hundred and fifty, numbered and signed. This is No. 42"; numbered and signed; inscribed to Fytton Armstrong, 1930 May 10.
    - "Dreams", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 133)
      Autograph manuscript, signed by author; an essay on prophetic dreams; accompanied by a leaf with presentation inscription from author to Mrs. Bernard F. Gimbel, 1927 May 20. Gift, 1958.
    - "The London Adventure," Pembroke, 1923 Aug 25 (Box 10, Folder 134-136)
      Autograph manuscript, signed. Gift, 1958.
    - "Meminisse/Dreams", 1927 Mar 31 (Box 10, Folder 137)
      Autograph manuscript, signed and dated. Purchase, 1945.
  - OTHER
    - Sweetser, Wesley D. "The Works of Arthur Machen: An Analysis and Bibliography", 1958 (Box 10, Folder 138-143)
      Ph.D. thesis, University of Colorado; typescript carbon. Gift, 1958.
    - Two photographs (copies) of Arthur Machen, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 144)
      Gift, 1940.
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile Papers in Box 11 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
  - Box 1, folder 32 (Box 11, Folder 145)
  - Box 1, folder 36 (Box 11, Folder 146)
  - Box 5, folder 125 (Box 11, Folder 147)